<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The shepheard, or A sermon, preached at a synode in Durisme Minster, vpon Tuesday, being the fifth of April. 1608. By Thomas Oxley, Master of Artes, and preacher of Gods word</title>
            <author>Oxley, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1609</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08769</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19053</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105795</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841521</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841521</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6109</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08769)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6109)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1324:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The shepheard, or A sermon, preached at a synode in Durisme Minster, vpon Tuesday, being the fifth of April. 1608. By Thomas Oxley, Master of Artes, and preacher of Gods word</title>
                  <author>Oxley, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by W. Jaggard] for Eleazer Edgar, and are to bee sold at his shop in Pauls church-yard, at the signe of the VVind-mill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1609.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A²  B-D⁴ E² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6109:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6109:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SHEPHEARD, OR A SERMON, PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT A SYNODE In <hi>Duriſme</hi> Minſter, vpon Tueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day, being the fifth of <hi>April.</hi> 1608.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Oxley,</hi> Maſter of Artes, and Preacher of Gods word.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 12.7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Hee that hath an Office, let him waite on his Office.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Bernar. Serm. 76. Super Cant.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>¶ Attendite vobis quicun<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> opus Miniſterij ſortiti eſtis, attendite inquam, vobis &amp; pretioſo depoſito quod vobis creditum est: Ciuitas est, vigilate ad cuſtodiam, concordiam<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>: Sponſa est, ſtudete ornatui: Oues ſunt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendite paſtui.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed for ELEAZAR EDGAR, and are to bee ſold at his Shop in Pauls Church-yard, at the Signe of the Wind-mill. 1609.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6109:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6109:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT Worſhipfull, my very louing Patrone, Maſter WILLIAM MORTON Archdeacon of <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme,</hi> Health and Happineſſe now, and euer.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y your leaue Sir, (Your ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie extraordinarie occaſions haue taught mee ſo much manners:) May it pleaſe you to be Godfather to the child, vnto which your ſelfe plaide the Grace-wife, by aſsigning your place to a perſon ſo vnworthy. At the Birth, you ſeem'd to ſmile on it; Nay, I will not ſpare to ſpeake, what you did not ſpare to doe, to commend it. It is now (as you ſee) learning to goe, and craues your hand, being otherwiſe weake of it ſelfe, to ſupport it. If it grieue not you to Patroniſe it; it cannot repent me to haue begotten it. I denie not, but that this ayre is an enemie dangerous and deadly; yet, I ſee not why this may not liue, if you miſlike it not: For, as for the body, I am ſure it is ſtrong and ſound; The parts, if not well faſhioned, yet not ill fauou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; The complexion, if not ſuch as may draw delight, yet ſuch as cold Countries commonly afford. There will not doubtleſſe, want ſome to maligne it, and to call it fooliſh Bratte, enuying my place in your affections, yet thoſe ſome (I thinke) of the ruder ſort, who feeling themſelues touch'd,
<pb facs="tcp:6109:3"/>
will perhaps begin to kicke: Will you not giue them leaue to ſhow what creatures they bee, <hi>Quis recalcitrabit aſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num?</hi> I am already hardned againſt their cenſures. For the more iudicious, if they will not loue the Father for the Childs ſake, yet I hope they will not hate the Child for the Godfathers ſake. To whom, how much the weale of our <hi>Northerne</hi> Church doeth owe, who haue knowen the North, and can be ignorant, you hauing (though not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether) for that is more to bee wiſhed for, then hoped for, yet as much as in you did lie, freed it from the tyrannie of two, no little troubleſome enemies, the preciſe <hi>Browniſt,</hi> and the peruerſe Papiſt, which worke is ſo much the more worthy, by how much the Perſons, with whom you had to deale, were reſolute, and mightie, that age being now cald by ſome, for the villanie executed then, <hi>THE MANS WORLD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what neede I talke of that, which both that, and this world can tell off: Goe on ſtill (good Sir) to oppoſe your ſelfe againſt the deprauers of the trueth, As you haue beene forward in the dayes of danger, ſo faint not now in the time of Peace: you haue at length with your lewde cries wakened Iuſtice, that for a long time had ſlept; ſuffer her not now againe to ſlumber. Bee ſtill a friend to thoſe that fauour, and follow learning; Beleeue me, it is no ſmall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, to deſerue well of ſuch. To conclude, and ſay, as much as I can ſay, Be your ſelfe ſtill, I know your occaſions, and I ceaſe to be troubleſome, wiſhing to you and yours, your beſt wiſhes and dayly furtherance in all ſpirituall graces. From my Chamber in New Caſtle. This <hi>10.</hi> of May. <hi>1609.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips wholly deuoted. THOMAS OXLEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:6109:3"/>
            <head>THE SHEPHEARD.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EZECHIEL. 34.2.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Should not the Shepheards feed the Flocks?</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Our preſence (Right Reuerend Father, and beloued brethren) puts me in mind of that cenſure ſometimes paſt by <hi>Haniball</hi> of <hi>Phormio</hi> the Philoſopher: The Storie is related by <hi>Plutarch.</hi> This <hi>Haniball,</hi> often happie in his victories againſt the Romanes, hauing at length found fortune leſſe friendly then he was wont: fled to <hi>Antiochus</hi> at Athens, where being brought by the Citizens to the ſchooles there, <hi>viſendi gratia,</hi> that he might ſee them, one <hi>Phormio</hi> a Philoſopher, (infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour to none of that age) for his better welcome, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertaines him with a Lecture full of warlicke diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline: This ended, euery one admiring the old mans dexteritie in ſo ſtrange a facultie, The Souldier was demaunded what hee thought; who anſwered,
<pb facs="tcp:6109:4"/>
               <hi>Se multos quidem deliros ſenes vidiſſe, neminem tamen</hi> PHORMIONE <hi>dementiorem:</hi> That hee had ſurely ſeene many doting old men, but more then <hi>Phormio,</hi> neuer any. <hi>Et merito ſane</hi> (ſaith <hi>Cicero</hi>) and ſurely he ſpoke to good purpoſe, for what could be a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of greater folly, then to ſee a Philoſopher, who had led his life in eaſe, and tranquilitie, who neuer yet did ſee a Campe, nor behold an enemie, before ſo worthy a Captaine as <hi>Haniball</hi> was, abſolute in knowledge, and perfect by experience, to diſcourſe of things militarie, for the which wee are more be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holding to vſe then meditation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>De meipſo narratur fabula.</hi> Me thinkes I am now in as bad caſe, or worſe, then the fond Philoſopher was then: for if hee was deſeruedly condemned by <hi>Haniball</hi> for ſpeaking of warre, whereof he was alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether ignorant, before ſo warie and expert a Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, as himſelfe was; what better meaſure can I expect from you? who hauing not yet bene inured, I cannot tell whether skilfull enough to giue foode to a flocke of mine owne, haue neuertheleſſe preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med at this time, (cald hither by him, to whom I owe my ſelfe) to deſcribe a Shepheards office, and that before you, approued paſtors of precious flocks, and fathers of faire families.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially, ſeeing this matter is nothing inferiour vnto that, wherein <hi>Haniball</hi> did glory, but ſo much the more excellent, by how much the enemie with whom wee haue to deale, is more dangerous, and deadly: neither is it to bee attained vnto, but with as much, or more experience then the other. Both
<pb facs="tcp:6109:4"/>
the perſons then before whom I am to ſpeake, ſo graue and ſo learned; and the thing whereof, ſo weighty, and worthy; might iuſtly haue enioyned me to ſilence, and ſtayed me, ſo vnskilfull a Marriner from ſayling in ſo vaſt an Ocean, where the rockes are great, and the dangers many; had not S. <hi>Bernard</hi> like a good Captaine thus incouraged me;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 20 1.</note> 
               <hi>Officium tuum attende, pelle pudorem conſideratione officii:</hi> Looke to thy tackling whereunto thou haſt taken thy ſelfe, and let the conſideration of thy office, banniſh baſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe. And goes yet further to comfort me, <hi>Non ſum (inquis) ad iſta ſufficiens, quaſi vero deuotio accepta non ſit, ex eo quod habes, non ex eo quod non habes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> Thou ſayeſt (ſaith he) I am not ſufficient to diſcharge this, as if thy deuotion be not accepted in regard of that which thou haſt, not of that which thou haſt not: prepare thy ſelfe to make anſwere for the talent which thou haſt receiued, and trouble thy ſelfe no further. <hi>Si multum accepiſti, da multum, Si modicum, &amp; id tribue.</hi> If it be much, giue much, if little, yet giue that. In that which I haue then, I promiſe my ſelfe prodigall enough, vouchſafe your acceptance, and I haue an abundant recompence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nonnè greges a paſtoribus paſcuntur?</hi> Should not the Shepheards feede their Flockes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Bucanus</hi> ſetting downe the commodities which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe from ſuch Synods as theſe, makes them two,<note place="margin">Inſtitu. theolog. loco <hi>42.</hi> de Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nodo.</note> and the firſt, this: <hi>Quia quod a multis quaeritur, Facilius inuenitur:</hi> Becauſe what is demaunded of many, is more eaſily found out. Loe here a queſtion pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to you all (beloued) not by any ſophiſticall
<pb facs="tcp:6109:5"/>
queſtioniſt, but by God himſelfe. And as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand is not very obſcure, ſo I hope the anſwere is not hard; let it bee my part to explaine the former, yours to determine the latter.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Occaſio.</note>This is the one and thirtieth Sermon which our Prophet hath made againſt the Shepheards of Iſrael, who haue bene the chiefe cauſe why the people haue led their liues ſo laſciuiouſly, and therefore are now worthily brought to this miſerie: for if they had not bene defectiue in their office, theſe had not bene ſo corrupt; The caſe being ſo, That ſuch as the prince is, ſuch is the people; like ſhepheard, like flocke; like maſter, like man.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Tempus.</note>As touching the time when it was vttered, it is not here expreſſed: ſome ſay it was before the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of the citty, when men were oppreſſed through the tyrannie of their rulers, and deluded by the lies of falſe Prophets. Saint <hi>Hierom</hi> tels vs, that thoſe Sermons following which haue no note of time, were had betwixt the twelfth yeere, and the twentie fiue of <hi>Iechonias</hi> captiuitie: but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it was before or after, it was eſpecially directed againſt the magiſtrates, aſwell Eccleſiaſticall, as Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticke, and in ſome ſort alſo may ſeeme to concerne the people themſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Partes.</note>The parts are fiue, firſt an accuſation, wherin God <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> doth taxe the Shepheards of Iſrael for neglecting the flocke committed to them, to feede themſelues: from the beginning of the firſt verſe, vnto the ende of the ſixt.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly a commination, wherein he threatens
<pb facs="tcp:6109:5"/>
them with the extremity of his iuſtice: as they haue ſowen ſo ſhall they reape, and no otherwiſe; for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as they haue contemned him, hee will ſet himſelfe againſt them: becauſe they haue beene care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe in keeping his flocke, he will haue a care to call them to an account; for that they haue not waited on their office, he will depriue them of their office, and becauſe they haue onely ſtudied to feede them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, they ſhall feed themſelues no more: from the ſeuenth verſe to the end of the tenth.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, a conſolation wherein God doth comfort <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> his Flocke, with promiſe, to gather them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to deliuer them from theſe euill ſhepheards, to feed them in a good paſture, to inſtruct them, defend, and care for them: from the 11. verſe to the 17.</p>
            <p>Fourthly a reprehenſion, wherein he reprooues <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> the riotouſneſſe of ſome ſheepe amongſt his flocke, their couetouſneſſe and crueltie: from the 17. to the 23.</p>
            <p>And fiftly, and laſtly, a comfortable promiſe, of <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> one, and he a faithfull Shepheard, euen Chriſt Ieſus, of whoſe kingdome he continues his Propheſie vnto the end of the chapter.</p>
            <p>In the whole you may obſerue, firſt, the difference <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> betwixt the good Shepheard, and the bad; what re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards are due to the one, what puniſhments to the other.</p>
            <p>And ſecondly, what the office of a painefull Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is, namely to checke the bad, and to cheriſh the good; to giue coraſiues to the one, comfortatiues to the other. This portion which I haue read vnto you, is a part of the firſt of theſe fiue parts, and indeede a
<pb facs="tcp:6109:6"/>
conferring and comparing of the duety of theſe Shepheards with their workes, quite contrary in the foure verſes following, propounded by an interro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, to note their impudence, who did peruerte and turne vp-ſide-downe the order of Nature: for Shepheards ſhould feede the flockes, not the flockes the Shepheards; whereas they fed on the flockes, eating the fatte, and cloathing themſelues with the woolle, vnworthy to beare the name, that were ſo farre from the nature.</p>
            <p>With both which, that we may be the better ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted, may it pleaſe you to obſerue in theſe fewe <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> words, theſe foure things: Firſt the Title that God giues vnto his Miniſters, they are <hi>Paſtores,</hi> Shephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, a duety that muſt not be denied, which is <hi>paſcere,</hi> to feede.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, the obiect of this duetie, <hi>non ſeipſos ſed greges,</hi> not themſelues but the flockes.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> And fourthly and laſtly, the neglect hereof in the firſt word <hi>Nonne?</hi> Should not? <hi>Should not the She<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheards feede the Flockes?</hi> of theſe foure, the Title, the Duety, the Obiect, and the Neglect.</p>
            <p>If we begin with the firſt: the firſt is the Title, <hi>Nomina ſunt notaererum</hi> (ſaith the Logitian) names are the notes of things;<note place="margin">Titulus.</note> and this name is not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome note: Gods Miniſters are called <hi>Paſtores,</hi> Shepheards <hi>a paſcendo,</hi> of feeding the Flocke.</p>
            <p>The name is common vnto them with Kings, for <hi>Homer</hi> cals them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Paſtors of the people, which notes their excellencie. The Notation is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
<pb facs="tcp:6109:6"/>
               <hi>ab effectis,</hi> from the effects; and ſince they are ſo called, the title tels vs, that they, who are rightly ſo intituled, muſt be <hi>Docti, diligentes, diſcreti:</hi> endowed firſt, with a power to performe: ſecondly, with a will to doe well: and thirdly with diſcretion to diſcerne; as if learning, loue, and prudence were <hi>Partes conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuae,</hi> the eſſentiall partes of a perfite Paſtor. If hee want the firſt, <hi>Nihil dat quod non habet,</hi> woe to the flocke; no man can giue what he hath not: if he hath the firſt and not the ſecond, as good want both, ſince the flocke muſt want howſoeuer: if both the firſt, and not the laſt, as good lacke all, for they had better giue nothing, then no good thing, or then ſome euil thing.</p>
            <p>He muſt haue theſe three at leaſt then, that would be, as many would be thought to be, true ſhepheards of Chriſts flocke: they doe well together, but being ſeparated, profite nothing. For to haue the flocke ſtarue for food, and the Shepheard not able to helpe them is a great miſery; to be able and not willing, is <hi>Immane</hi> crueltie; to be both able and willing, and yet want diſcretion how, when, what, and to whom to giue, is but a fooliſh, and fruitleſſe induſtry.</p>
            <p>Firſt then he muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> learned, for Shephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> are called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> Seers,<note place="margin">Doctus.</note> Phil. 3.7. and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſayeth the Poet) they ſee twice as much as others who are ſeene in learning.<note place="margin">Menander.</note> This ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the ſtaffe of life, the ſhephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards ſtaffe, without which hee can neither ſupport himſelfe, nor rule others. <hi>In literis prudens inuenerit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jn Epiſtola qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam.</note> 
               <hi>vnde ſapientior fiat, ibi bellator reperit vnde animi vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute roboretur</hi> &amp;c. In learning (ſaith <hi>Chryſologus</hi>) the wiſe man hath found what hath made him more skilfull:
<pb facs="tcp:6109:7"/>
The Warriour how to confirme his mind againſt all dangers: The Prince, how to gouerne his people with equality, <hi>Nec aliqua in mundo poteſt eſſe fortuna, quam literarum non augeat glorioſa notitia.</hi> Nor can there be any condition in the world, which the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble knowledge of learning doth not make more ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable. Wherefore <hi>Socrates</hi> the wiſeſt Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher that euer was, being demaunded what creature was moſt excellent, made anſwere, <hi>Homo doctrina or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus:</hi> A man beautified with learning. If this be ſo neceſſarie and commendable in euery calling, how much more in the Miniſter and Meſſenger of God, who is the eye of the world, and as it were a Sunne in the Firmament of the Church, to diſperſe the clouds of ignorance, and giue light vnto ſuch as ſit in darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. And what maruell if wee call ſuch Sunnes, when our Sauiour himſelfe ſaid vnto ſuch, <hi>Vos eſtis lux mundi,</hi> you are the light of the world, Matth. 5.14 For as God in the beginning of the world did ſet the Sunne and other lights in the heauens, to ſhine vpon the earth; ſo in the firmament of the Church hee hath placed Biſhops as Sunnes (who onely proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may be ſaid to be Sunnes, becauſe while others are but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Seers, 1. Pet. 5.2. they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. Ouerſeers) and other teachers, as the reſt of the lights and ſtarres, to enlighten the mindes of men, and to impart to others, what they haue receiued from God themſelues.</p>
            <p>If therefore it belong to a Shepheard to teach his flocke, how can he performe this, if he hath not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning? The Sunne cannot giue light if it be eclipſed, no more can a Paſtour performe his duetie, who is
<pb facs="tcp:6109:7"/>
drowned in the deepes of darke ignorance. Where the caſe ſtands ſo, what can follow but that which our Sauiour himſelfe ſaid? <hi>If the light which is in you be darkenes, how great is that darkenes?</hi> Matth. 6.23. What is there in the whole office of a Shepheard that ſtands not in great neede of the light of learning? for to iudge of the grounds of faith, to take away contentions in the Church, to decide Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, to inſtruct the people, to diſcerne the Leaper from him that is cleane; learning is ſo neceſſary, that without it, he can no more determine any thing, then hee that is blinde can iudge of colours. Wherefore the Lord purpoſing to beſtowe a benefite vpon his people, promiſeth them Paſtors according to his owne heart, who ſhould feed them with knowledge, and vnderſtanding. Ier. 3.15. Which benefite will ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare the greater, if we compare it with the contrary, for that muſt needs be a great good, the defect wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is ſo great an euill. And what an euill that is, the Prophet <hi>Iſayah</hi> will tell vs, who reckoning vp the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries of the people, makes this one, that God would take from them the Iudge, and the Prophet, the pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, and the aged, the Counſellor, and the eloquent man. Iſa. 3.2. When the Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi> was ready to lay downe his Tabernacle, he did appoint, that <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> an holy man, and very learned, ſhould be his ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, and gaue commandement that the ſame <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> ſhould ſignifie ſo much in his letters to <hi>Iames</hi> the brother of our Lord, then Biſhop at <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And feare not (ſaith he) leaſt hee be much ſorrowfull for my death, ſeeing he cannot doubt but that I ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:6109:8"/>
for righteouſnes ſake: <hi>Erit autem ei grande ſolatium, ſi didicerit quòd poſt me non imperitus aliquis,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Primo Tom. Concil.</note> 
               <hi>aut ignorans Diuini verbi miſterium, &amp; Eccleſiaſtici ordinis diſcipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam, vel doctrinae regulam neſciens, ſuſceperit Cathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dram meam.</hi> And it will be a great comfort vnto him to know, That no Illiterate Prelate, ignorant of Gods word, and Church diſcipline, That no ſtranger to Learning, and good Arts ſhall vſurpe my Chaire: For he knoweth well that if ſome rude and vnskilfull Perſon ſhould take vpon him the place of a Paſtour, the flocke wandring in the Thickets of ignorance, muſt needes runne headlong to deſtruction. Hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to are the words of <hi>Peter,</hi> as <hi>Clement</hi> himſelfe relateth them in his Epiſtle to <hi>Iames</hi> at Ieruſalem, how true, I cannot tell, yet profitable I am ſure for our inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Since it appeares hereby, how neceſſarie a thing Learning is in the place of a Paſtor. I will there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore paſſe from this to the next, with that good ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a godly man, <hi>Ridiculoſa res eſt, vel potius pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſa,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gilbert.</note> 
               <hi>ſpeculator caecus, Doctor inſcius, proecurſor claudus, Praelatus negligens, &amp; praeco mutus.</hi> A blind Seer, a lame forerunner, a negligent Prelate, and a dumbe crier, is a thing ridiculous or rather dangerous.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As he muſt be learned, ſo muſt he be louing, The firſt makes him able,<note place="margin">Diligens.</note> the ſecond willing: <hi>Though hee ſpeake with tongues of men, and Angels, yet if he hath not loue, hee is as ſounding braſſe, or a tinkling Cymball.</hi> 1. Cor. 13.1. And this likewiſe ariſeth out of the no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of the word. For it is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>quaſi</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> which ſignifieth a Sheepe, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to deſire earneſtly, or to ſeeke, for it hath both. Which loue how great it ſhould bee who cannot coniecture by Chriſts
<pb facs="tcp:6109:8"/>
thrice iterated Queſtion to <hi>Peter? Simon Ioannes, dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis me plus his, &amp;c. Iona, loueſt thou me more then theſe? Feede my ſheepe.</hi> Ioh. 21.15. As if he ſhould haue ſaid, If thou loueſt me truely, and ſincerely, if thou deſire to glorifie my Name, if thou loue my Sheepe, as it ſeemes thou doſt, whoſe ſafetie is more regarded of me, then mine owne life; if for all the benefits thou haſt receiued, thou deſire to gratifie me in any part, and with loue to requite loue, feede my Sheepe which I haue fed with my deareſt blood; for whileſt thou feedeſt thoſe, thou feedeſt me in them, thou fats me, and doſt nouriſh me, and whatſoeuer thou be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowes on them, thou conferres on me; for I am hee who haue ſometime ſpoken it,<note place="margin">Mat. 25.40.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoeuer you haue done to the leaſt of theſe, ye haue done it vnto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This loue then of the Shepheard to the Flocke, proceedes from the loue which hee beareth vnto Chriſt, for hee doeth not ſay (which is worthy your obſeruation) <hi>If thou loue my ſheepe, feede them,</hi> which ſhould ſeeme a good conſequent, <hi>Cum probatio dilecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onis</hi> (as <hi>S. Gregorie</hi> ſaith) <hi>exhibitio est operis:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. in Homil.</note> When the proofe of loue is the performance of the worke. But he ſaith, <hi>Si diligis me, If thou loue me feed my ſheepe.</hi> As if hee ſhould ſay, If thou loue me, thou ough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt likewiſe to loue thoſe things that are mine, and belong to me, and there is nothing more mine, then my Sheepe are, to whom I haue giuen my fleſh for foode, and my blood for drinke, whom by my death, I haue recald to life: If therefore nothing bee more deere to me the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> life, how much more deere are thoſe, for whom I haue humbled my ſelfe to death. The ſumme then of this, is, Thoſe that loue Chriſt, will
<pb facs="tcp:6109:9"/>
loue his Flocke, and thoſe that loue it will feede it. And for our encouragement herein,<note place="margin">Super. Ezech.</note> 
               <hi>Gregorie</hi> tels vs, <hi>Quod nullum poteſt eſse Deo gratius ſacrificium, quam Cura animarum,</hi> That there can be no Sacrifice more acceptable vnto God, then the Cure of ſoules: And this Cure doth God require at euery mans handes, who hath a Cure. As he did of <hi>Moſes,</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> himſelfe doth witneſſe; when he Complaines vnto the Lord, ſaying, <hi>Haue I conceiued all this people, or haue I begotten them, that thou ſhouldeſt ſay vnto me, Carie them in thy boſome (as a Nurſe beareth the ſucking child,) &amp;c.</hi> Numb. 1.12. In which kind how zealous S. <hi>Paul</hi> was, himſelfe can tell vs, who thus much is bold to ſay of himſelfe, and his fellowes to the <hi>Theſſalonians, We haue beene gentle among you, euen as a Nurſe cheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth her children:</hi> Thus being affectionate towards you, our goodwill was to haue dealt vnto you, not the Goſpel of God onely, but alſo our owne ſoules, becauſe yee were deare vnto vs. 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.8. What is it that a Nurſe will denie vnto her child, and what will not <hi>Paul</hi> performe to this people? He was ready to doe any thing, becauſe he was affectionate, his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection made him ready.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> To theſe two adde the third; and that is <hi>Prudence,</hi> he muſt bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Prudens.</note> wiſe and diſcreet likewiſe, that muſt be a good Shepheard: For as thoſe who are skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full in Phiſickes Art, doe not miniſter all things to all men, nor at all times, but to euery one according to the qualitie of the diſeaſe, or the complexion, and conſtitution of the body of the patient: So muſt he that is a healthfull feeder of Gods flocke, bee wiſe to conſider the nature of each ſheepe, and the ſtrength
<pb facs="tcp:6109:9"/>
of their ſtomackes, and to miniſter foode there after, to ſome milke, to ſome fleſh: Some muſt haue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations, ſome conſolations, ſome muſt be gently intreated, others ſeuerely reprehended: Sometimes Wine will be neceſſarie, ſometimes Oyle, ſometimes one thing, ſometimes another.</p>
            <p>This Prudence, <hi>Paul</hi> requires in a Paſtor, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2. And that good old <hi>Abbat</hi> alluding to his owne profeſſion, Cals it <hi>Abbatiſſam virtutum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> The Abba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſe, the Lady or chiefe of all vertues; which who ſo wanteth, may rightly ſuſpect himſelfe, ſince nothing is more neceſſary by Gods own teſtimonie,<note place="margin">Mat. 10.13.</note> Thus are Miniſters called Paſtors, feeders, to ſhew that they muſt bee like Nurſes in abilitie, in affection, and in diſcretion.</p>
            <p>Now you that are Shepheards, who haue taken vpon you the feeding of Chriſts flocke, which hee with ſuch care committed vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> &amp; conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to you, Examine your ſelues vpon theſe three Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, whether you be able, if able, whether willing, if willing, whether wiſe enough to diſcharge ſo great a charge, whilſt I ſet this Shepheard, which I haue brought into the field thus furniſhed, to attend on his Office.</p>
            <p>Next to the Title, followed the Duety, which <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> is <hi>Paſcere,</hi> to feede: what is he,<note place="margin">Officium.</note> and what call you him, ſayeth one in the Dialogue, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Plato in Mino<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> who is excellent in feeding a flocke of ſheepe? Anſwere is made <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, A Shepheard, the name is taken from the office; hee therefore that fulfilleth not the one, cannot chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge the other: He muſt feede, that would be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
<pb facs="tcp:6109:10"/>
a Feeder; and the neceſſitie of this Conſequent, was to <hi>Dauid</hi> an occaſion of great comfort, for cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling God his Shepheard, hee triumphs in it, and hee giues this reaſon, he can therefore want nothing, God will feed him in greene paſtures. Pſal. 23.1.2.</p>
            <p>This is a large field, and the further I walke in it, the more ſubiect I am to wander: I will therefore follow the path wherein Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> hath trod, and take him to be my guide, who vpon thoſe words of our Sauiour vnto <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Serm. <hi>2.</hi> Reſurr. domini.</note> 
               <hi>paſce oues meas,</hi> Feed my Sheepe, hath theſe; <hi>paſce mente, paſce ore, paſce opere,</hi> and then expounds himſelfe, <hi>paſce animi oratione, ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bi exhortatione, exemplï exhibitione.</hi> Feed with prayer, feed with preaching, feed with thy life, and godly conuerſation. Theſe as the three former, doe well together, but being a ſunder profit little.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The moſt precious foode of the ſoule, is the word of God,<note place="margin">Paſce ore.</note> This is that which periſheth not, but endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth vnto euerlaſting life. Iohn. 6.27. And this is conferd vpon the flocke by the action of preaching: wherein how induſtrious the Apoſtles were, none that are conuerſant in the Scriptures can be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant: What was the great charge giuen by S. <hi>Paul</hi> to his Scholler <hi>Timothie?</hi> was it not to preach the word, to bee inſtant in ſeaſon, and out of ſeaſon, to improue, rebuke, and to exhort with all long ſuffering and doctrine? 2. Tim. 4.2.</p>
            <p>This he was to performe, as he would anſwere be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the tribunall ſeat of God, when the ſecrets of all hearts ſhall be diſcloſed. And this he confirmes with his owne inſtance, when being to depart from <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> he committed the keeping of Gods flocke vnto
<pb facs="tcp:6109:10"/>
the Elders of the Church with this <hi>memento,</hi> Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that by the ſpace of three yeeres, I ceaſed not to warne euery one both night and day with teares. <hi>Acts</hi> 20.31.</p>
            <p>To whom was it ſaid, but to Shepheards, <hi>Negoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amini, dum venio,</hi> Labour till I come, <hi>Luke</hi> 19.13. <hi>Quod profecto negotium, tunc verè nos agimus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Libr.</hi> 2. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 39.</note> 
               <hi>Si viuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do &amp; loquendo proximorum animas lucramur</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Gregorie</hi>) which buſineſſe wee ſurely then per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme, if by our preaching and liuing, we gaine the ſoules of men, if wee rebuke and reproue ſuch as are obſtinate, if we comfort the penitent, if we ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then the weake, heale the infirme, bind vp the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, ſeeke what is loſt, and bring againe what was driuen away, by the example of the good Shepheard. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 34.16.</p>
            <p>As they muſt preach, ſo muſt they pray, for when <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> they haue ſtudied the word diligently,<note place="margin">Mente.</note> preached it purely, exhorted gently, reproued ſharpely, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured euery way ſincerely, to what end will all this come: <hi>Paul</hi> may Plant, <hi>Apollo</hi> may Water, but it is God that muſt giue the increaſe, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.6.</p>
            <p>As therefore Shepheards are the mouth of God to ſpeake vnto the people, ſo muſt they be the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples mouth to pray vnto the Lord: And herein wee haue our Sauiour himſelfe for an example, who albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it he was very God, aſwell as man, and had power of himſelfe to ſanctifie the eares and hearts of his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers, and to make his preaching as profitable as him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe liſted; yet he prayed to his Father both for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and them, <hi>Iohn</hi> 17.9. Whoſe example the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles followed: <hi>Paul</hi> did bend his knees for the <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6109:11"/>
(As himſelfe profeſſeth) vnto the Father of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, that he would grant them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the riches of his glory, that they might be ſtrengthened by his ſpirit in the inner man, <hi>Ephe.</hi> 3.14</p>
            <p>And deepely proteſteth to the Romanes, calling God to witneſſe, that without ceaſing, he made men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of them alwayes in his prayers, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.9. And he thankes God that without ceaſing he had remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of his Scholler <hi>Timothie</hi> in his prayers, night, and day. 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.3.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> To theſe two, adde <hi>ſanctitie</hi> of life, and no more can be required:<note place="margin">Oper<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> be vnto them that beleeue (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothie</hi>) an example in word, and in conuerſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.12. For he that ſaith, and doth not, is like him who hauing mony, can put it to no other vſe but to tell it;<note place="margin">Plutar. de pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectu morum.</note> which <hi>Anacharſis</hi> the Scythian ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſpake of the Grecians, who were great Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers in words, but in life, and manners, moſt lewd, and light.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Jn Lacon.</note>
               <hi>Plutarch</hi> tels a Story to this purpoſe, of a certaine old man, who hauing a long time walked vp and down amongſt the Grecians at the games of <hi>Olimpus,</hi> and finding no place to reſt him in, at length he went among the <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> where not onely all the children did riſe to giue him place, but many of the men likewiſe; which when the Grecians, as many of them as were preſent and did obſerue, did with great applauſe approue of; The old man cries out, <hi>He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> miſertam! Omnes graeci norini quid ſit honeſtum, ſed eo ſoli vtuntur Lacedemonii.</hi> All the Grecians doe know what is honeſt, but the <hi>Lacedemonians</hi> one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly practiſe it. I would not our Shepheards proued Grecians, and the flockes <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:6109:11"/>
then that follow, which the Lord ſpoke by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, <hi>They that ſhould miniſter the law, knew me not, and the Paſtors alſo offended againſt me.</hi> Iere. 2.8.</p>
            <p>Gods miniſters are called the <hi>ſalt of the earth;</hi> and if the ſalt be vnſauorie,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.13.</note> wherewith then can it ſeaſon other things. <hi>Qui ſibi nequam, Cui bonus!</hi> hee that cannot rule himſelfe, is not fit to rule others. They are called <hi>lux mundi,</hi> the light of the world,<note place="margin">Mat. 5.14.</note> for the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of their vertues, If therefore that light be put vnder a buſhell, how can it enlighten others? It was a good ſaying, that of <hi>Senecaes, Eum elige tibi doctorem, quem magis admireris, cum videris, quam cum audieris:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 34.</note> make choice of ſuch a teacher, as thou maiſt admire more hauing ſeene him, then when thou heardſt him. Whoſe life is more commendable then his learning. And therefore <hi>Paul</hi> commaunds <hi>Titus,</hi> that aboue all things, he ſhould ſhow himſelfe an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of good workes, <hi>Titus</hi> 2.7. For, <hi>plus mouent exempla quam verba.</hi> Examples do moue more then precepts,<note place="margin">Gregorie.</note> and a good life then a good leſſon. <hi>Et facilius homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ad bene faciendum exemplis, quam verbis inuitantur:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Origen.</note> and men are incited ſooner by works then by words, and by liues then by lawes to doe well.</p>
            <p>And this manner of teaching is very admirable, and powerfull to inflame the minds of men with a deſire to doe well. A good ſouldier, <hi>Non ſentit ſua, cum benigni ducis contuetur vulnera:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Bernard.</note> feeles not his owne wounds, when hee ſees the ſoares of his kinde Captaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> (as <hi>Tullie</hi> tels it) neuer ſaid to his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, <hi>Goe,</hi> but <hi>Come:</hi> for the labour ſeemes alwaies the leſſe, when hee that commands, cannot be idle.
<pb facs="tcp:6109:12"/>
Let Shepheards learne to inſtruct their flockes, as <hi>Abimilech</hi> did his ſubiects, by making himſelfe an example; who when he had cut downe boughs, and bare them on his ſhoulders, ſpoke to thoſe that were with him, <hi>Quemadmodum vidiſtis me facientem, ita &amp; vos facite.</hi> As you haue ſeene me doe, ſo doe you, <hi>Iudg.</hi> 9.48.</p>
            <p>But as the godly life of good Shepheards is power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to perſwade the people vnto good, So the lewd life of bad Shepheards is of as much, or farre greater force, to draw them vnto euil: ſince ſuch is our nature, that we learne nothing ſooner then filthines, &amp; forget nothing more hardly. And therefore ſaith Saint <hi>Gregorie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. in paſt.</note> There is no man more daungerous in the Church, then hee that liues wickedly and carries a name, or degree of ſanctitie: whereupon ſaith Saint <hi>Auſten,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. lib. de paſt.</note> 
               <hi>Omnis qui male viuit in conſpectu eorum, quibus praepoſitus eſt, quantum in ipſo eſt, occidit.</hi> He that liues badly in the ſight of thoſe ouer whom he is placed, as much as in him is, is a murderer. Wherefore I will conclude this point with that of Saint <hi>Bernard</hi> to <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. <hi>2.</hi> de conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat.</note> 
               <hi>Monſtroſa res eſt, gradus ſummus, &amp; animus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fimus, ſedes prima, &amp; vitaima, Lingua magniloqua, &amp; manus otioſa, ſermo multus, &amp; fructus nullus, vultus gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uis, &amp; actus leuis, caput Canum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> et cor vanum, facies ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goſa, &amp; lingua nugoſa, ingen authoritas, &amp; nutans ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitas.</hi> And thus much of the Shepheards office.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
               <hi>Should not the Shepheards feed?</hi> But whom ſhould they feede?<note place="margin">Obiectum.</note> This is our third part, the obiect of the duetie.<note place="margin">Paſce gregem.</note> 
               <hi>Non ſeipſos ſed greges,</hi> Not themſelues, but the flockes: <hi>Should not the Shepheards feede the flockes?</hi> The Elders which are among you, I beſeech (ſaith S.
<pb facs="tcp:6109:12"/>
               <hi>Peter</hi>) feede the flocke of God, 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.2. Be dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent (ſaith <hi>Salomon</hi>) to know the ſtate of thy flocke, and take heede to thy heards, <hi>Prou.</hi> 27.23. Two things there are of ſpeciall moment to perſuade here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, The firſt whereof is the price, the ſecond the <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> perill. If we reſpect the firſt, experience tels vs,<note place="margin">Praetium.</note> that we muſt regard what we hold deereſt, we loue moſt, and what is moſt worth; And what I pray you, is more precious then the ſafetie of ſoules, for which the onely begotten ſonne of God did not ſticke to ſhed his blood, to lay downe his life, to humble him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to an opprobrious death?</p>
            <p>If the ſecond, what is ſubiect to more apparant <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> dangers,<note place="margin">Periculum.</note> ſince our life is a warfare (as <hi>Iob</hi> cals it) vpon earth. In which wee haue to deale with three cruell and bloody enemies, The world, the fleſh, and the diuell. The firſt vaine and curious, the ſecond, fraile and rebellious, the third euill and malitious. Saint <hi>Auſtine</hi> compares our life vnto a ſea, and ſuch an one, <hi>Vbi &amp; ventus eſt &amp; procellae non deſunt tentationum.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tract. <hi>14.</hi> in Ioan.</note> Wherein there are both windes of aduerſitie, and ſtormes of temptations. And Saint <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> to the Aegean ſea, where there are <hi>venti, anguſtiae, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribdis, ſtagna, ſyrtes,</hi> winds, waues, rocks, ſands, very hard to be ſayled. In the Marſilian ſea, (ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard) ex decem nauibus, vix vna aliqua periclitatur,</hi> of ten ſhips ſcarce any one is endangered, but in the ſea of this world, often ſoules, ſcarce any one is ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. To be ſhort (for I would not likewiſe trouble you with tediouſneſſe) amongſt all the dangers of this world, tell me of any, either more imminent, or eminent then this of ſoules, and amongſt all thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:6109:13"/>
things that are had in price, what is more precious? what is gold, what is riches, pearles, kingdomes, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, yea and whatſoeuer elſe is contained within the circuit of this vniuerſall, if it be weighed with the worth of one ſoule? The leaſt of theſe then might be a ſufficient motiue to ſtirre vp each Shepheard to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect this obiect, were there nothing elſe, but there is ſomething yet further, as namely the accompt which they are to yeeld, for all muſt come to an accompt, and euery one ſhall receiue his wages, according to his labours.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 3.8.</note> To him that hath bene faithfull, God ſhall giue an incorruptible crowne of glory, 1. Pet. 5.4. But to him that deſtroyeth, and ſcattereth the flocke, wo ſhall be vnto him (ſaith the Lord) <hi>Ier. 23.1. Shepheards muſt feed the flocks then, not feed on the flocks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now from hence may ſome couetous accurſed cai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe, ſpider like, ſuck poyſon, and gather this concluſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Since Shepheards muſt feed the flocks, the flocks muſt not feed the Shepheards; the Shepheards muſt not at all feed on the flockes.</p>
            <p>There are too many, I know, that lay hold on ſuch latchets: But this is not our Prophets meaning, who albeit he condemne thoſe, that make that their grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt care, yet is he not ſo careleſſe of them as altogther to reſtraine them. For who planteth a vineyard, &amp; ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth not the fruit therof?<note place="margin">1. Cor. 9.7.</note> or who feedeth a flocke, and eateth not the milke of the flock? If we ſow vnto you ſpirituall things, (ſaith the Apoſtle) is it a great thing if we reap your carnall things,<note place="margin">Galat. 6.7.</note> 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11. Be not you then deceiued (beloued) for God is not mocked. As you ſow ſo ſhall you reape; you are called a flock, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared vnto ſheepe; then which, no creature is more
<pb facs="tcp:6109:13"/>
ſimple, whence came the Prouerbe <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, after the maner of ſheepe. And as this ought to teach you <hi>vitae innocentia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> to be like vnto Sheep, <hi>ſine fraude, dolo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>
               </hi> without guile, or deceit: patience to beare, meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to forbeare; ſo likewiſe it preacheth to you hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mility, to acknoledge your weakneſſe, and ignorance, and conſequently obedience to your Paſtors; with a will to giue what the Apoſtle commaunds: namely double honour to thoſe that rule well, eſpecially to ſuch as labour in the word, and doctrine. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. And thus much likewiſe of the <hi>Obiect</hi> of the duety.</p>
            <p>Theſe three thus curiouſly handled (for the matter better befits the Preſſe then the Pulpit) I haue almoſt fulfild my promiſe, and vndergone my taske. <hi>Quod reliquum eſt, veſtrum eſt.</hi> It remaines now for you that are Shepheards, to reſolue the queſtion. And I pray you tell me, <hi>Should not the Shepheard feede the flocke?</hi> Doubtleſſe the concluſion paſſeth for currant, your ſilence ſhall aſſure mee your conſent. How comes it to paſſe then, that this duetie is neglected; and the flockes are vnfedde: to reſolue this wee muſt come to our laſt part, the <hi>Neglect:</hi> lend mee your eares a little, I will not long detaine you.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nonne? Should not the Shepheards feede the flockes?</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Three things there were (you heard) which did inable a Shepheard in his office; <hi>Learning, Loue,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neglect.</note> and <hi>Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi> The want of theſe, or of ſome two, or one of theſe, is the mother of this monſter.</p>
            <p>The firſt was <hi>Learning,</hi> And the want of this, is very <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> plentifull amongſt vs;<note place="margin">Defect. doctr.</note> our Shepheards moſt of them being like vnto thoſe, whom the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes in his 56. Chapter, 10. verſe. They are blind,
<pb facs="tcp:6109:14"/>
they haue no knowledge, they cannot vnderſtand, they are dumbe dogs, they cannot barke, they lie and ſleepe, and delight in ſleeping. If euer Countrie was accurſed in this kind, it is this of ours, being placed in the midſt of a famous Iland, as the obiect of diſgrace, for both ends to point at, or rather the refuſe of two Realmes, as if both diſdained it, aſhamed to challenge it. How many blind ſeers may be ſeene here, foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh teachers, lame forerunners, negligent Paſtors, and dumbe cryers: Shepheards indeed, but fitter to keepe ſheepe, then to care for ſoules. <hi>Bubulcos non paſtores,</hi> Neatheards, not feeding Shepheards; As if thoſe ouer whom they are placed, were beaſts, and not men, irrationall animals, not reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. If you aske me then, how chance the flockes are no better looked vnto? I anſwere, becauſe the Seers are blind: If you demaund further, why blinde men are made ſeers; I muſt reply with Saint <hi>Bernard.</hi> The fault is in the <hi>ouerſeers,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 152.</note> 
               <hi>Dant Epiſcopi ſanctum Canibus, &amp; Margaritas porcis,</hi> Biſhops giue that which is holy, (as orders, and Church liuings) vnto dogs, and pearles vnto ſwine, <hi>Et illi conuerſi, conculcant eas!</hi> It wont to be a great queſtion, betwixt the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines, and Lawyers, if a place were void, and two in election, and both worthy, whither it was lawfull that the election might be made of the leſſe worthie or not? This was long in deciding; The Lawyers held that it was lawfull: the Diuines, eſpecially ſuch as imbraced the doctrine of <hi>Aquinas,</hi> that it was not: Till at length the Counſell of <hi>Trent</hi> did determine it, decreeing, that they did ſinne mortally, <hi>Qui digniores, &amp; Eccleſiae magis vtiles pastores, praeficere non curaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:6109:14"/>
who did not prouide that the more worthy and profitable Paſtors, ſhould be put in authoritie.</p>
            <p>But it were to bee wiſhed in theſe times of ours, that election were made onely of worthy men, for there needs no contention, ſince the places are many, and the number of thoſe not great, yet ſufficient: But this is more to be wiſhed for, then hoped for, ſince it may be our plaint now, that he complained of in his time. <hi>Quid vſitatius nunc eſt, quam his conferre Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiae beneficia, qui non quia virtute pollent, literiſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſunt egregie inſtituti, Sed quia diu famulati ſunt, quia fideliter Epiſcoporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> redditus procurarint, auxerint:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Silueſt. de cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rup.</note> 
               <hi>quia gynaecia praelatorum arte temperauerint, vel quia ſint agnati, ſiue affines, ſiue domeſtici lurcones, qui ad colendn<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </hi> Bacchum, <hi>&amp; Cererem magis idonei habeantur, quam ad Cultum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinum, ad docendum populum, ad gubernationem Eccleſiae. Ideo iſtis videatis Epiſcopos malle ſacerdotia, quam piis eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> viris conferre, ita vt vel nunc, vel nunqua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accidit, quod rudis quidem ſed facetus tamen cecinit vates.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Mos eſt praelatis, prebendas non dare gratis,</l>
               <l>Sed bene nummatis, vel eorum ſanguine natis.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>A ſecond cauſe of the neglect of this dutie, is want <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> of <hi>Loue;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Defect. charit.</note> ſome there are who are able to feede the flocke, but will not; becauſe they doe not loue, they cannot labour. Such loue not Chriſt, for if they did, they would feede his Sheepe. Are ſuch Shepheards? they are Wolues: Are ſuch Hennes? they are Kites: doe ſuch feede the Sheepe? they feed on the ſheepe: they eate the fat, they cloath them with the wooll, they kill thoſe that are fed, and they feede not the Sheepe. The weake they ſtrengthen not, the ſicke they heale not, the broken they binde not vp, they
<pb facs="tcp:6109:15"/>
bring not againe what was driuen away, they ſeeke not what is loſt, but with cruelty, and rigor doe they rule. <hi>Ezech.</hi> 34.4.</p>
            <p>And I would there were no ſuch falſe Prophets a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt vs, who loue themſelues, and the world ſo much, as they can impart no part of it to others. <hi>Loue ſeeketh not her owne things</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. And it was his pleaſure to pleaſe all men, in all things, not ſeeking his owne profit, but the profit of others, that they might be ſaued, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.33. But it is our pleaſure to take paines onely to pleaſure our ſelues, and to bee ſo induſtrious in this kind, as forgetting the dignitie whereunto we are cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, (though vnworthy) to betake our ſelues wholly to the plow, the ſpade, the rake, and the flaile, play the merchant, ſollicite cauſes, ſupply the places of ſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, and ſuch like baſe offices, ſo common in our cold Countrie, that vnleſſe a man be thus egregiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly qualified, hee can haue no place in the affections of our frozen patrons.</p>
            <p>Are ſuch <hi>Shepheards?</hi> take away the Metaphor, &amp; make them (as indeed they are) carnall ſhepheards, and I will bring no other but the very ſheepe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to ſpeake to them, yet in their owne tongue, leaſt they vnderſtand not S. <hi>Bernards</hi> language.<note place="margin">Bernard. Epiſt. <hi>42.</hi>
               </note> And let the ſpeech be thus. If you that are our Shepheards goe crooked, like vs who are your ſheepe, carrying your countenance downeward, ſtill looking to the earth; and to pamper the belly, euer ſeeke for foode; <hi>In quo diſtinguimur,</hi> wherein doe we differ? will you ſee how the ſilly beaſt, makes ſimple beaſts on them. <hi>Si venerit lupus, Quis praeuidebit, &amp; occurret?</hi> If the
<pb facs="tcp:6109:15"/>
Wolfe ſhall come, who ſhall foreſee him and preuent him? Such ſheepe are in a bad caſe; yet if they bee ſlaine, God hath vowed to require their blood at ſuch Shepheards hands, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 3.20.</p>
            <p>The third, and laſt cauſe of this neglect, is want of <hi>Prudence.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Defect. pruden.</note> This may come through too much know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> for <hi>Scientia inflat</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge puffeth vp, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.1. And of this euen the greateſt ſchollers many times doe labour, who vpon a priuate conceit of their owne worth, doe oft abuſe good things to the hurt of others. Thoſe that are ſo wiſe are no company for honeſt Athenians. Though this want of <hi>Prudence</hi> be <hi>monſtrum,</hi> yet it is <hi>mirum:</hi> though it be a monſter in a miniſter, yet it is a mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaile in many of ours, for the greateſt Clarkes (they ſay) are not alwayes the wiſeſt men. Our Clarkes may be wiſe then, for I am ſure, they are none of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt. But why ſhould I ſtand ſeeking theſe in euery miniſter? <hi>Cum ex quouis ſtipite non fit mercurius,</hi> Since euery perſon will not make a Prieſt. The want of theſe three, you ſee then, is the reaſon, why the flocke doe want: ſome want learning, therefore they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not <hi>Preach.</hi> Some want <hi>Loue,</hi> therefore they cannot <hi>Pray.</hi> And ſome want <hi>Prudence,</hi> and therefore they cannot <hi>Edifie</hi> by their good example.</p>
            <p>Thus ſome would, and cannot; ſome can, and will not; and many neither can, nor would, nor doe.</p>
            <p>What remaines now for me, but to draw to a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion.<note place="margin">Vſus <hi>1.</hi> ad Epiſc.</note> If firſt you (my honorable Lord) will giue me leaue to leaue one vſe with you. <hi>Attendito tibi, &amp; vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſo gregi, in quo ſpiritus ſanctus te poſuit epiſcopum.</hi> Take heede to your ſelfe, and to all the flocke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb facs="tcp:6109:16"/>
the holy Ghoſt hath made you ouerſeer. See then both to the Sheepe, and Shepheards; and thoſe euils which you could not ſtop in the beginning, yet ſtay them in their proceeding. See that Shepheards feed the flocks, and not altogether feede on the flockes. But there is an other thing which craues your honors care; take heed that the flocks feed not on the Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards. This was a thing our Prophet neuer drea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of. Such vnnaturall dealing neuer came with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the compaſſe of his conceit, and yet ſuch Wolues there are within your fields in ſheepes clothing, who kill their Shepheards, wounding ſome in their good name, opprobriouſly; ſome in their bodies, dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly; ſome in their eſtate, iniuriouſly; renting both the perſons, and their perſonages in peeces. Are ſuch ſheepe? they are better in the Shambles, then in the field. Are there ſuch Shepheards, and in your flock? Yes, They are ſicke, heale them: they are weake, ſtrengthen them: they are broken, bind them vp: that when you ſhall come to giue vp your accompt, you may be able to ſay, as the good Shepheard ſayd, <hi>Thoſe that thou gaueſt me, haue I kept, and none of them is lost.</hi> Ioh. 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>You that are Shepheards (beloued) feede your flockes which depend vpon you; caring for them, not by conſtraint, but willingly, not for filthie lucre, but of a readie mind; And when the chiefe Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard ſhall appeare, ye ſhall receiue an incorruptible crowne of glory. 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.4.</p>
            <p>You that are ſheepe, loue your Shepheards, and giue to them that rule well double honour, eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:6109:16"/>
to ſuch as labour in the word and doctrine. And as you ſow, ſo ſhall you reape.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Now he that hath an office, let him looke to his office.</hi> I muſt conclude: Brethren, farewell, be perfect, be of good comfort, be of one mind, liue in peace, and the God of loue and peace ſhall be with you. Now the very God of peace ſanctifie you, throughout, and I pray God that your whole ſpirit, and ſoule, and body, may be kept blameleſſe vnto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. To whom with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt, three perſons, and one euerliuing God, we aſcribe, As due, all honour, and glory, praiſe, power, dignitie, and dominion, now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
